<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hello world | Catch me code]]></title>
  <link href="http://jonaslu.github.com/blog/categories/hello-world/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jonaslu.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-24T22:01:33+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jonaslu.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonas Lundberg]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World!]]></title>
    <link href="http://jonaslu.github.com/blog/2013/02/05/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-05T21:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jonaslu.github.com/blog/2013/02/05/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Phew, just had to get that off my chest. It has been brewing for a couple of years now.</p>

<h2>And who are you then?</h2>

<p>Hacking stuff started at an early age - writing basic on an old 286 (no scoffing! It had an extra math co-processor chip thank you very much). Mostly because I wanted to see what I could make the computer do. Since then some education before now having worked in the software industry for about 7 years now on several different sites. First as a consultant before landing at my current workplace as a  software developer and part time team lead.</p>

<h2>Why write this blog?</h2>

<p>As with any topic, first stage - learning the craft, second stage - actively employing it and third stage - starting to contribute and setting out to bring the field forward. This is one of those outlets, where hopefully I can contribute in some small way to the advancement of the craft.</p>

<p>Nothing evolves in vacuum. The greatest ideas are usually juxtapositions of other great ideas. I've been continually amazed at what people can come up with - its never just the sum of the parts. So hopefully this will go the same way, ideas bouncing off each other building something greater than the individual parts.</p>

<p>So the bar is set aptly high, all needed now is just producing content.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
