<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: software estimates | Catch me code]]></title>
  <link href="http://catchmecode.com/blog/categories/software-estimates/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://catchmecode.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-16T21:30:40+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://catchmecode.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonas Lundberg]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[jonasl@catchmecode.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Estimates: the 95% done syndrome]]></title>
    <link href="http://catchmecode.com/blog/2013/10/20/estimates-the-95-percent-done-syndrome/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-20T22:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://catchmecode.com/blog/2013/10/20/estimates-the-95-percent-done-syndrome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;ve <a href="/blog/2013/09/27/software-estimates-the-plus-100h-joke/">already discussed</a> the black art of software estimates and how you might practically approach getting a reasonable digit. There&rsquo;s another side to software estimates: missing deadlines.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>I love deadlines. I like the whooshing sound they make as they fly by.</p><footer><strong>Douglas Adams</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<h2>It&rsquo;s 95% done</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve been in the business more than a couple of months, you know the drill. You&rsquo;re not going to make it and you (and possibly everyone else) knows it. But you soldier on, quietly grinding your teeth and on the inside hoping for a small miracle. And when (as always) the miracle fails to manifest itself come due date you have to confess &ndash; &ldquo;I&rsquo;m behind&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Its so easy to get there. Even if there&rsquo;s weekly follow ups and beautiful gantt schemes. Its usually in one of two ways:</p>

<p>a) The vague response: &ldquo;Yeah, i&rsquo;m only slightly behind schedule. Its 95% done &ndash; only cleaning up and tests left. I&rsquo;m sure well make up for it in the next week&rdquo;. But has it ever?</p>

<p>b) The tough guy: &ldquo;Its done when its done&rdquo;. This is just as unhelpful. Remember your clients clients? They&rsquo;re going to look elsewhere if all your client has is &ldquo;its ready when its ready&rdquo;. And then you&rsquo;ll be out of business.</p>

<h2>Flag up</h2>

<p>Cause it takes courage not wind up at due date with nothing to show. The minute you realize you&rsquo;re gonna botch the time limit &ndash; let someone know. Flag up, as loud and as clear as you can. Yes, you might get scalded. That&rsquo;s part of work. Be prepared for this by having numbers on how far you&rsquo;ve gotten, what work you think remains, and where the estimate went wrong. Also, if needed take time to calmly explain again what the word estimate means. This part is like a loosing a band aid. Its going to hurt &ndash; might as well get it off fast and promptly.</p>

<p>Otherwise the hurt is going to come in two ways &ndash; first on yourself in the form of stress. You will dance to the old familiar tune: hope for the best, maybe some magic will happen on the way, skimp a little on the tests. The second in form of a larger scalding when due date is up and you have nothing to show for.</p>

<h2>Negotiate</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s something I&rsquo;ve learned: There&rsquo;s always room for negotiation. I&rsquo;ve yet to meet a client or recipient of our software that wasn&rsquo;t happier getting <strong>something</strong> on the scheduled delivery date than getting everything later (at least after they&rsquo;ve calmed down). Yeah. The clients. Those who pay you. See &ndash; chances are that they in turn have clients. And that your clients have made commitments to their clients in turn.</p>

<p>If they get on the due date that you&rsquo;re not going to make it &ndash; they&rsquo;ll get scaldings from their clients etc and since you&rsquo;re the producer &ndash; the endline of the food chain, guess where that heat is going to be forwarded? Even if your client is an end consumer, they&rsquo;re going to look elsewhere if you keep postponing the delivery date.</p>

<h2>Benefits for everyone!</h2>

<p>What you are giving your client when you flag up a delay directly is time to re-plan. Maybe they can launch without all the bells and whistles? Maybe there&rsquo;s manual workarounds that can be solved with a later delivery? Ask them what the core functionality is and how you can get as close as possible given the time that is left. Work with them and negotiate.</p>

<p>What you are giving yourself is room to breathe. Your deadline might still be tight, you now you&rsquo;ve got an honest chance again. And that saves a lot of aspirins and sleepless nights. Not to mention that the best software is written under achievable deadlines.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Estimates: the +100h joke]]></title>
    <link href="http://catchmecode.com/blog/2013/09/27/software-estimates-the-plus-100h-joke/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-27T21:33:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://catchmecode.com/blog/2013/09/27/software-estimates-the-plus-100h-joke</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We have a saying in my team, that we &ldquo;pull a number out of our ass&rdquo; if an estimate on the spot is larger than 100h hours. As with any joke, there&rsquo;s a core of truth to this. Here&rsquo;s why: You don&rsquo;t have a feel for how long a task spanning 40h of work is (never mind above 100h). 8h is tangible, 16h might be tangible, 40h is not tangible and 100h is funny.</p>

<p>The time estimate is then multiplied by the usual offset factor based on historical estimates. But, it has happened that if we make too many jokes about the number being random the time estimate is raised one notch more because those jokes shows that we still really don&rsquo;t know.</p>

<h2>Is it tangible?</h2>

<p>What usually happens with an estimate above 16h:
You start out with grand plans, you make things extra nice. Refactor this, change that, there&rsquo;s still plenty of time left, right? Time looms on, and you wake up. Half the time is gone, you have still 75% of the work left, never mind the testing. And the estimate goes out the window.</p>

<p>At 40h this is prolonged by the fact that 40h just feels so much more. But work wise its just as much as 5*8h. When the 20th hour rolls by, you should be as done as you are on the 4th hour of an 8h estimate.</p>

<h2>What can you do</h2>

<p>Break it down. If any of your chunked points are above say 25h, chunk it again. The goal it to get it as close to tangible (aim for 8h) chunks as possible. At the end of each chunk you know what should be ready. Look at it like many small 8h tasks that just happen to be connected to a bigger task.</p>

<p>Be aware of that having done 8h chunks may give you a false security of having all the bits in place. Even with nice sequential 8h chunks on a larger estimate &ndash; the larger the estimate, the more off we are. This is because missing stuff hides on the edges of those 8h chunks. The interplay between those chunks takes more time, but are hard to factor in.</p>

<p>Also be aware of any gray areas or stuff you don&rsquo;t know that well. Here is the other mistake we often do. We oversimplify things. If you are any bit unsure, go look at the code, think about the edits you&rsquo;d make. Touch it, smell it, get some feel for it. Write down the line-numbers and files you&rsquo;d change in the estimate.</p>

<h2>Log time spent</h2>

<p>Unfortunately work does not always align sequentially with the 8h chunks. You often have to skip between chunks. Try to keep some percentage of time / work left on each chunk. At regular intervals, stop and look at where you are, where you should be and if you&rsquo;re off. The earlier you know you&rsquo;re off the earlier you can start thinking about how to prioritize the time you have left before shipping date.</p>

<h2>Its just an estimate</h2>

<p>When you get to it, don&rsquo;t forget that its just that: an <strong>estimate</strong> &ndash; that will keep changing until you&rsquo;re done. Replan, re-proritize, even re-estimate if you notice (and you will notice if its above 16h) that you&rsquo;re off.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
